I went to Spain a few months ago
ذهبت الي اسبانيا منذ بضعة اشهر
and I had the best foie gras of my life.
واكلت افضل فطيرة لكبد الاوز في حياتي
The best culinary experience of my life.
أفضل تجربة الطهي في حياتي
Because what I saw, I'm convinced, is the future of cooking.
وبفضل مارأيت،اقتنعت ان هذا هو مستقبل الطهي
Ridiculous, right?
مثير للسخرية هذا الأمر أليس كذلك
Foie gras and the future of cooking.
فطيرة الأوز ومستقبل الطهي!
There's not a food today that's more maligned than foie gras, right?
اليست فطيرة الأوز اكثر طعام يعاب هذه الأيام
I mean, it's crucified.
اعني انه قد تم صلبه
It was outlawed in Chicago for a while.
وكان محظورا في شيكاغو لفترة من الزمن
It's pending here in California, and just recently in New York.
وهي معلقة الان في كاليفورنيا.والان قريبا في نيويورك
It's like if you're a chef and you put it on your menu,
فاذا كنت طاهيا ووضعتها في قائمتك
you risk being attacked.
فانت عرضة للهجوم
Really, it happened here in San Francisco to a famous chef.
حقيقة ... لقد حدث هذا لاحد الطهاة هنا في سان فرانسيسكو
I'm not saying that there's not a rationale
انا لا اقول انه لا يوجد هناك منحى غير عقلاني او ضرب من الخبل
for being opposed to foie gras.
فيما يتعلق بفطيرة الاوز
The reasons usually just boil down to the gavage, which is the force feeding.
فعادة يتم إطعام الاوز بالغصب .. أي بالتزقيم
Basically you take a goose or a duck
فأنت اساسا تاخذ البطة او الوزة
and you force feed a ton of grain down its throat.
وترغمها بوضع الاف الأطنان من الحبوب في حلقها
More grain in a couple of weeks than it would ever get in a lifetime.
كمية من الحبوب في اسبوعين اكبر ممما قد تأكلها في حياتها كلها
Its liver expands by eight times.
فتتمدد كبدها اكبر بثماني مرات
Suffice to say it's like -- it's not the prettiest picture of sustainable farming.
يكفي القول بأن ذلك مثل -- ان تلك ليست الصورة الأجمل للزراعة المستدامة
The problem for us chefs is that it's so freakin' delicious.
المشكلة بالنسبة لنا نحن الطهاة انها لذيذة جدا
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I mean, I love the stuff.
انا اعني ذلك فانا احب ذلك الطعم
It is fatty, it's sweet, it's silky, it's unctuous.
فهو دسم ولذيذ حريري ومدهن
It makes everything else you put it with taste incredible.
فهو يجعل اي شي تضعه معه ذي طعم رائع
Can we produce a menu that's delicious without foie gras?
فهل حقا يمكننا ان نصنع قائمة طعام لذيذ من دون كبد الأوز
Yes, sure.
نعم يمكن
You can also bike the Tour de France without steroids, right?
كما يمكنك الفوز في سباق فرنسا للدراجات بدون منشطات ، أليس كذلك؟
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Not a lot of people are doing it.
لا كثير من الناس حقا يفعلون ذلك
And for good reason.
ولسبب وجيه ايضا
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So several months ago, a friend of mine sent me this link to this guy,
منذ عده اشهر ارسل لي صديقي رابطا لهذا الرجل
Eduardo Sousa.
ادواردو سوزا
Eduardo is doing what he calls natural foie gras.
ادواردو يقوم بعمل ماأسميه كبد الوز الطبيعي
Natural foie gras.
كبد الوز الطبيعي
What's natural about foie gras?
ماهو الطبيعي حول فطيرة الأوز؟
To take advantage of when the temperature drops in the fall,
لتأخذ افضيلة حينما تنخفض درجات الحرارة في الخريف
geese and ducks gorge on food
حيث يقوم الوز والبط بالتهام الطعام
to prepare for the harsh realities of winter.
لتتحضر لواقع الشتاء المؤلم
And the rest of the year they're free to roam around Eduardo's land
وبقية السنة فهي حره لتحوم في ارض ادواردو
and eat what they want.
وتاكل ماتريد
So no gavage, no force feeding,
فليس هنالك تزقيم او اكل بالقوة
no factory-like conditions, no cruelty.
لا اوضاع مشابهة للصناعة لا قسوة
And it's shockingly not a new idea.
والمحير والصادم انها ليست بالفكرة الجديدة
His great-granddad started -- Patería de Sousa -- in 1812.
حيث كان جد ادواردو بارتيرا دي سوزا يفعل ذلك منذ العام 1812
And they've been doing it quietly ever since.
وظلت العائلة تفعل ذلك من ذلك الحين في صمت
That is until last year,
وكل ذلك يستمر حتى العام المنصرم
when Eduardo won the Coup de Coeur,
حيث فاز ادواردو بكأس دي كيور
the coveted French gastronomic prize.
وهي جائزة فرنسية لتذوق الطعام
It's like the Olympics of food products.
فهي بمثابة اولومبياد الطعام
He placed first for his foie gras.
وكان الأول بفطيرة الأوز خاصته
Big, big problem.
مشكلة مشكلة كبيرة جدا
As he said to me, that really pissed the French off.
كما قال هو حيث انه فعلا اغضب الفرنسيين جدا
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
He said it sort of gleefully.
هو قال ذلك بنوع من البهجة
It was all over the papers.
كل ذلك كان على الورق
I read about it. It was in Le Monde.
وقرات عنه في لاموند
"Spanish chef accused ... " -- and the French accused him.
"طاهي فرنسي متهم" ـ والذين يتهمونه هم الفرنسيون
"Spanish chef accused of cheating."
اتهموه بالغش
They accused him of paying off the judges.
وبأنه قدم الرشوة للحكام
They implicated actually, the Spanish government, amazingly.
لقد اتهموا فعلا الحكومة الأسبانية. مثير
Huh, amazing.
اليس كذلك مثير
A huge scandal for a few weeks.
فضيحة كبيرة استمرت لأسابيع عديدة
Couldn't find a shred of evidence.
لم استطع ان اجد رابطا للحدث
Now, look at the guy.
الأن انظروا الي الرجل
He doesn't look like a guy who's paying off French judges
فهو لا يبدو كرجل يمكن أن يرشو حكاما فرنسيين
for his foie gras.
لأجل فطيرة كبد أوز
So that died down, and very soon afterward,
لذلك انتهي الأمر بعد فترة قليلة ونسي
new controversy.
الجديد في الجدل
He shouldn't win because it's not foie gras.
انه لم يفز بسبب الوصفة وصفة كبد الاوز
It's not foie gras because it's not gavage.
فهي ليست فطيرة اوز لانها لاتحتوي علي تسمين
There's no force feeding.
فليس هناك تزقيم = اجبار على الاكل
So by definition, he's lying and should be disqualified.
لذلك من التعريف فانه يكذب ولذلك يجب ان يُنحي
As funny as it sounds, articulating it now and reading about it --
مضحك كما يبدو ، ابحث عنه واقرا عنه الأن
actually, if we had talked about it before this controversy,
حقيقة لو تكلمنا عنه قبل هذا الخلاف
I would have said, "That's kind of true."
كنت لأقول ان هذا قد يكون حقيقة
You know, foie gras by definition, force feeding, it's gavage,
ففطيرة الأوز كانت تعني عند التسمين والتزقيم والأكل بالقوة قبل تحول مفاهيمي
and that's what you get when you want foie gras.
وهذا ماتحصل عليه عندما تتطلب فطيرة الأوز
That is, until I went to Eduardo's farm in Extremadura,
هذا هو ، حتي ذهبت الي مزرعة ادواردو في اكسترامادوريا
50 miles north of Seville, right on the Portugal border.
50 ميلا الى الشمال من اشبيلية ، وتماماً على الحدود البرتغال.
I saw first-hand a system that is incredibly complex
شاهدت بأم عيني نظاماً معقداً بشكل لا يصدق
and then at the same time, like everything beautiful in nature,
وفي نفس الوقت مثله مثل اي شي جميل في الطبيعة
is utterly simple.
بكل ماتعني الكلمة من معني البساطة
And he said to me, really from the first moment,
وقال هو لي منذ اللحظة الاولي
my life's work is to give the geese what they want.
عملي في الحياة هو أن اعطي الأوز ماتريد
He repeated that about 50 times in the two days I was with him.
وكرر ذلك حوالي خمسين مرة في اليومين الذين قضيتهما بصحبته
I'm just here to give the geese what they want.
انا هنا فقط لأعطي الاوز ماتريد
Actually, when I showed up he was lying down with the geese with his cell phone
في الحقيقة عندما قدمت اليه كان مستلقيا في الأرض مع اوزاته وهاتفه الخلوي
taking pictures of them
ياخذ صورا لهن
like his children in the grass.
مثل الأطفال علي العشب
Amazing.
مدهش
He's really just in love with -- he's at one with --
هو حقا يحبهم ــ هو الوحيد في ذلك معهم
he's the goose whisperer.
إنه الهامس للأوز
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And when I was speaking to him, you know, I thought,
وبينما كنت اتكلم معه كنت أعتقد
like I'm speaking to you now, right,
كانه كما اتكلم معكم الأن طبيعي
but sort of in the middle of my questions, my excited questions,
لكن في منتصف حديثي وأسئلتي، اسئلتي المشوقة
because the more I got to know him and his system,
وبفضل الكثير الذي عرفته عنه وعن نظامه
the more exciting this whole idea became.
هذه الفكره المدهشة كلها اصبحت
He kept going like this to me.
استمر بتحريك يديه هكذا
And I thought, OK, excited Jew from New York, right?
وكنت اعتقد انه يعني حينا. يهودي متحمس من نيويورك أليس كذلك؟
I'm talking a little too aggressively, whatever,
أنا أتحدث قليلا بعدائية ،علي اي حال
so you know, I slowed down.
علي كل حال انا قللت حديثي
And finally, by the end of the day I was like,
واخيرا في نهاية اليوم كنت
Ed-uar-do, you know like this?
مثل ادوارده مثل هذا؟
But he was still going like this.
لكن هو مازال علي ماهو عليه وحركة يديه
I figured it out.
اخيرا اكتشفت ماذا يقصد
I was speaking too loudly.
انا كنت اتحدث بصوت عالي
So I hushed my voice.
فخفضت صوتي
I kind of like asked these questions and chatted with him through a translator
سألت نوع من مثل هذه الأسئلة وتجاذب اطراف الحديث معه من خلال مترجم
in kind of a half whisper.
في وضع مثل نصف هامس
And he stopped doing this.
فأوقفت ذلك
And amazingly, the geese who were on the other side of the paddock when I was around --
وبشكل مثير للدهشة ، والإوز الذين كانوا على الجانب الآخر من الحلبة عندما كنت في جميع أنحاء --
"Get the hell away from this kid!" --
بعيدات جدا عن جحيم هذا الطفل
when I lowered my voice, they all came right up to us.
عندما كنت اعلي صوتي اتوا لجانبي تماما!
Right up to us, like right up to here.
قريبات جدا بهذا القرب
Right along the fence line.
على طول خط الجدار.
And fence line was amazing in itself.
والجدار نفسه كان مدهشا
The fence -- like this conception of fence that we have
حيث كان بغير المفهوم الذي نعرفه عن السياج
it's totally backward with him.
انها مختلفة تماما
The electricity on this fiberglass fence
حيث كانت الكهرباء في هذا السياج المصنوع من الفايبر
is only on the outside.
من الخارج فقط
He rewired it. He invented it.
حيث انه اعاد تمديد الكهرباء به واختراعه
I've never seen it. Have you?
انا لم ارى مثله هل رأيتم أنتم؟
You fence in animals. You electrify the inside.
انتم تكهربون الداخل اليس كذلك والخارج
He doesn't.
هو لا يفعل ذلك
He electrifies only the outside.
هو فقط يكهرب الخارج فقط
Why?
لماذا؟
Because he said to me that he felt like the geese --
لانه كما أخبرني احس بأن الأوز
and he proved this actually, not just a conceit, he proved this --
واثبت ذلك لي ليس فقط كفكرة ولكن بالبرهان
the geese felt manipulated when they were imprisoned in their little paddocks.
ان الاوز تحس بالتلاعب عندما يتم سجنها
Even though they were imprisoned in this Garden of Eden
حتي ولو تم سجنهم في جنة عدن
with figs and everything else.
مع التين وكل المميزات الأخري
He felt like they felt manipulated.
فهو يحس بالذل والتلاعب
So he got rid of the electricity,
فهو لذلك تخلص من الكهرباء
he got rid of current on the inside
التي هي بالداخل
and kept it on the outside,
وابقي التي بالخارج
so it would protect them against coyotes and other predators.
ليحمي الأوز من الثعالب والحيوانات الأخرى
Now, what happened?
الأن ماذا حدث؟
They ate, and he showed me on a chart,
اكلت الاوزات واطلعني هو علي تخطيط هندسي
how they ate about 20 percent more feed to feed their livers.
حول كيف انهن أكلن 20 بالمئة ليطعمن اكبادهن
The landscape is incredible.
وارضه كانت رائعة
I mean, his farm is incredible.
اعني كل مزرعته كانت رائعة
It really is the Garden of Eden.
هو حقا منسق جنة عدن
There's figs and everything else there for the taking.
والتين وكل شي يمكن ان تتكلم عنه
And the irony of ironies is because Extremadura, the area --
وسخرية السخرية ان منطقة اكسترامادوريا
what does Extremadura mean?
تعني حرفياً ..
Extra hard land, right?
تعني الأرض القاسية جدا اليس كذلك؟
Extra difficult. Extra hard.
قاسية جدا وعصية جدا
But over four generations, he and his family
ولكن علي مر العصور هو وعائلته
have literally transformed this extra hard land into a tasting menu.
غيروا حرفيا الارض العصية لقائمة تجارب
Upgrades the life for these geese.
وطوروا حياة هذه الأوزات
And they are allowed to take whatever they want.
وجعلوهن ياخذن مايردن
Another irony, the double irony
والسخرية الأخري الأكبر
is that on the figs and the olives,
ان ذلك يحتوي علي التين والزيتون
Eduardo can make more money selling those
ادواردو يمكنه ان يجني اموالا من ذلك
than he can on the foie gras.
اكثر من اموال فطيرة الأوز
He doesn't care.
لكنه لايهتم
He lets them take what they want and he says,
هو فقط يجعلهن يأخذن مايردن
"Usually, it's about 50 percent. They're very fair."
وعادة يبيع نصفهن وهذا عادل جدا
The other 50 percent, he takes and he sells and he makes money on them.
ويبقي علي البقية بعد بيع الأولي
Part of the income for his farm.
كجزء من دخل المزرعة
A big part of his income for his farm.
وهي الجزء الأكبر من دخل المزرعة
But he never controls it.
لكنه ليس هو من يتحكم بهذا الدخل
They get what they want,
فالأوز يحصل علي مايريد
they leave the rest for me and I sell it.
ويتركن البقية له ولعائلته
His biggest obstacle, really, was the marketplace,
لكن اكبر عقبة له كان السوق
which demands these days bright yellow foie gras.
الذي يطلب هذه الايام فطيرة اوز فاقعة الصفرة
That's how I've been trained.
وهذا ماتم تدريبي عليه
You want to look and see what good foie gras is,
فانت تريد ان ترى فطيرة الاوز ذات
it's got to be bright yellow.
صفار فاقع جدا
It's the indication that it's the best foie gras.
وتلك دلالة علي افضل نوع لفطيرة الاوز
Well, because he doesn't force feed,
حسنا لكن لانه لم يرغمها ويزقمها
because he doesn't gavage tons of corn,
ولانها لم تطعم بالقوة اطنان من حب الذرة الصفراء
his livers were pretty grey.
لقد كانت اكباده رمادية
Or they were.
او كما كانت قبل
But he found this wild plant called the Lupin bush.
ان يجد نبته برية تسمي لوبن بوش
The Lupin bush, it's all around Extremadura.
كانت تنبت حول منطقته
He let it go to seed, he took the seeds,
واخذ هذه النبته وزرع حبوبها
he planted it on his 30 acres, all around.
في حوالي 30 ايكرا من ارضه
And the geese love the Lupin bush.
والاوزات احببنها
Not for the bush, but for the seeds.
ليس للورود ولكن لحبوبها
And when they eat the seeds, their foie gras turns yellow.
وعندما اكلنها انقلبت اكبادها صفراء ......!!!
Radioactive yellow.
اصفرا مشعا
Bright yellow.
مشعا جدا
Of the highest quality foie gras yellow I've ever seen.
كاجود كبدة صفراء يمكن ان تراها
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So I'm listening to all this, you know, and I'm like,
وانا استمعت لكل ذلك وكنت كما تعرفون
is this guy for real? Is he making some of this up?
هل هذا الرجل حقيقي؟هل اختلق بعضا من هذا
Is he like, you know -- because he seemed to have an answer for everything,
لانه كما بدا انه لديه اجابة لكل سؤال
and it was always nature.
ودائما كانت الإجابة هي الطبيعة
It was never him.
لم يكن هو ابدا
And I was like, you know, I always get a little, like,
وانا كنت مثل من يزداد صغرا كل مرة
weirded out by people who deflect everything away from themselves.
مبهورا بأناس بعيدين جدا عن كل شي حتي انفسهم
Because, really, they want you to look at themselves, right?
لانهم حقا يريدون ان يبقوا مع انفسهم اليس كذلك؟
But he deflected everything away from his ingenuity
لكنه حيد كل شي ببراعته
into working with his landscape.
للعمل مع الطبيعة
So it's like, here I am, I'm on the fence about this guy,
فهو مثل وانا الأن علي الحياد
but increasingly, eating up his every word.
لكن فعليا أكل كل كلمة هو يقولها اكلا
And we're sitting there, and I hear [clapping] from a distance, so I look over.
وبينما هو جالس هناك اذا بي اسمع تصفيق من بعيد ونظرت الي من حولي
And he grabs my arm and the translator's,
واذا به يمسك بيدي والمترجم يقول لي
and ducks us under a bush and says, "Watch this."
وهو يخفينا تحت العشب ويقول شاهد هذا
"Shush," he says again for the 500th time to me.
"شششش" قالها للمرة 500 لي
"Shush, watch this."
"شششش" شاهد هذا
And this squadron of geese come over.
وهذا سرب من الإوز يأتي
[Clapping]
تصفيق
And they're getting louder, louder, louder, like really loud, right over us.
وزاد الصوت اعلى واعلى حتى حلقت فوقنا
And like airport traffic control, as they start to go past us
ومثل المطار وتحكمه .... بدات الأوزات الطائرة تهبط
they're called back -- and they're called back and back and back.
ومن في الارض تنادي المحلقة والعكس بالعكس
And then they circle around.
ومن ثم حلقن بصورة دائرية
And his geese are calling up now to the wild geese.
والأن الأوزات المحلية تنادي البرية
[Clapping]
تصفيق
And the wild geese are calling down.
والبرية تنادي من بالأسفل
And it's getting louder and louder and they circle and circle
ويزيد ويتحلقن ويتحلقن
and they land.
والأن يهبطن!!!
And I'm just saying, "No way."
وانا اقول مندهشا لا يمكن مستحيل
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
No way.
لايمكن
And I look at Eduardo, who's near tears looking at this,
وانظر الي ادواردو وهو قريب ينظر الينا
and I say, "You're telling me that your geese are calling to the wild geese
واقول "هل انت تخبرني ان ان اوزاتك تنادي الأوزات البرية لتبقي
to say come for a visit?"
لزيارة قصيرة
And he says, "No, no, no.
لكنه قال لا لا لا
They've come to stay."
انهن يأتين ليبقين ويستقرن
They've come to stay?
وانا اقول يستقرن هنا؟
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
It's like the DNA of a goose is to fly south in the winter, right?
اليس شريط الحمض النووي يقودهن للطيران للجنوب في الشتاء؟؟
I said that. I said "Isn't that what they're put on this Earth for?
اليس ذلك منذ خلق الأرض
To fly south in the winter and north when it gets warm?"
ان تسافر الي الجنوب في الشتاء والي الشمال في الدفء
He said, "No, no, no.
لكنه قال لا لا لا
Their DNA is to find the conditions that are conducive to life.
حمضهم النووي هو ان تجد اوضاعا ممكنة ومهيئة للحياة
To happiness.
للسعادة
They find it here.
التي يجدنها هناك
They don't need anything more."
انهن لا يحتجن لشي اكثر من هذا
They stop. They mate with his domesticated geese,
توقفن الأن وانضممن الي الوز المستانسة
and his flock continues.
واستمرت رعيته في الزيادة
Think about that for a minute.
فكر لدقيقة في ذلك
It's brilliant, right?
انه ذكي وخلاق اليس كذلك؟
Imagine -- I don't know, imagine a hog farm
تخيل-- انا لا ادري تخيل فقط مزرعة خنازير
in, like, North Carolina,
في شمالي كارولينا
and a wild pig comes upon a factory farm
وجاءت بعض الخنازير البرية لمصنع خنازير
and decides to stay.
وققرن ان يبقين
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So how did it taste?
اذا كيف سيكون طعمها
I finally got to taste it before I left.
وقبل مغادرتي اتيحت لي فرصة التذوق
He took me to his neighborhood restaurant
فقام بأخذي الي مطعم محلي
and he served me some of his foie gras, confit de foie gras.
وقدم لي بعضا من فطيرة الأوز المعدلة
It was incredible.
وكانت مذهلة جدا
And the problem with saying that, of course, is that
لكن المشكلة طبعا كم أقول
you know, at this point it risks hyperbole really easily.
منذ تلك اللحظة خطورة المقارنة اصبحت سهلة
And I'd like to make a metaphor, but I don't have one really.
وأود ان اقوم بعمل استعارة لكنها ليست لدي واحدة
I was drinking this guy's Kool-Aid so much,
فانا كنت اشرب كحول هذا الرجل كثيرا
he could have served me goose feathers and I would have been like,
ويمكن ان يكون ماقدمه لي هو ريش الاوز ولا ادري
this guy's a genius, you know?
ذلك الرجل حقا ذكي
I'm really in love with him at this point.
انا حقا احبه الأن في هذه النقطة
But it truly was the best foie gras of my life.
لكن حقا تلك كانت افضل فطيرة اوز في حياتي
So much so that I don't think I had ever really had foie gras until that moment.
وفي تلك اللحظة حقا لم أكن اكلت فطيرة اوز في حياتي
I'd had something that was called foie gras.
لقد كنت اتناول شيئا يدعي فطيرة الأوز
But this was transformative. Really transformative.
ذلك كان تحولا حقيقيا
And I say to you, I might not stick to this,
وكما اقول لكم انا قد لا ألتزم بذلك
but I don't think I'll ever serve foie gras on my menu again
لكن انا لن اضع فطيرة الاوز علي قائمتي بعد الأن
because of that taste experience with Eduardo.
لاجل الطعم الذي تذوقته لدي ادواردو
It was sweet, it was unctuous.
لقد كان جميلا لقد كان مذهلاً
It had all the qualities of foie gras,
لقد كان يحتوي كل جودة فطيرة الأوز
but its fat had a lot of integrity and a lot of honesty.
لكن دهنه كان حقيقا ومتماسكا وصادقا
And you could taste herbs, you could taste spices.
ويمكنك ان تتحسس طعم العشب والتوابل
And I kept -- I said, you know, I swear to God I tasted star anise.
وانا احتفظت-- بطعم وجدته وهو طعم اليانسون
I was sure of it.
وكنت متاكدا من ذلك
And I'm not like some super taster, you know?
وانا لم أكن كمتذوق خيالي
But I can taste things.
لكن استطيع ان اتذوق
There's 100 percent star anise in there.
لكن هناك اعطيت 100% احقية النجمة لذلك الطعم
And he says, "No."
وهو قال نعم
And I ended up like going down the spices,
وانا كنت كمن يعوم في التوابل
and finally, it was like, OK, salt and pepper,
وفي النهاية قلت نعم هناك ملح وفلفل
thinking he's salted and peppered his liver.
لقد اضاف الملح والفلفل فقط للكبد !!
But no.
لكن لا
He takes the liver when he harvests the foie gras,
لقد اخذ الكبد عندما حصد الفطائر
he sticks them in this jar
ووضعهم في جرة
and he confits it.
ووضع المكونات معه
No salt, no pepper, no oil, no spices.
لم يضف اي ملح او توابل
What?
ماذا؟
We went back out for the final tour of the farm,
ثم عدنا في جولة اخيرة للمزرعة
and he showed me the wild pepper plants
واراني الفلفل البري لديه
and the plants that he made sure existed on his farm for salinity.
والمكونات كلها كانت مزروعة في مزرعته المملحة!!
He doesn't need salt and pepper.
لم يحتاج للملح والفلفل
And he doesn't need spices, because he's got this potpourri of herbs and flavors
ولم يحتاج للبهارات .لأنه حصل على هذا الأعشاب والنكهات مجففة
that his geese love to gorge on.
من خلال حب اوزاته لاكلها
I turned to him at the end of the meal,
والتفت اليه عند نهاية الوجبة
and it's a question I asked several times,
وكان السؤال الذي سالته مرات عديدة
and he hadn't, kind of, answered me directly,
وهو لم يجب علي بصورة مباشرة
but I said, "Now look, you're in Spain,
لكنه قال انت في اسبانيا
some of the greatest chefs in the world are --
حيث هناك اعظم الشيفات في العالم
Ferran Adria, the preeminent chef of the world today, not that far from you.
فيرا ادريا افضل طاهي في العالم الأن وليس بعيدا منك
How come you don't give him this?
كيف لك ان لا تعطيه هذا؟
How come no one's really heard of you?"
كيف انه لايوجد احد يسمع عنك
And it may be because of the wine,
وانا ربما بفضل النبيذ
or it may be because of my excitement,
وربما بفضل تحمسي وانبهاري
he answered me directly and he said, "Because chefs don't deserve my foie gras."
رد علي قائلا"لانهم لايستحقون اوزي"
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And he was right.
وكان هو علي حق
He was right.
لقد كان علي حق
Chefs take foie gras and they make it their own.
الطهاة ياخذون الأوز لكنهم يصنعون خاصتهم بأنفسهم
They create a dish
انهم يصنعون صحنا
where all the vectors point at us.
حيث كل الخطوط تشير الينا
With Eduardo it's about the expression of nature.
مع ادواردو وشرح الحياة
And as he said, I think fittingly,
وكما قال هو ملائمة لهذا
it's a gift from God, with God saying, you've done good work.
اعتقد انها هدية من الله وان الله يقول له لقد قمت بعمل جيد
Simple.
بسيط
I flew home, I'm on the flight with my little black book
واستقللت الطائرة للوطن. ومعي كتابي الاسود الصغير
and I took, you know, pages and pages of notes about it.
واخذت صفحات عن هذا الرجل
I really was moved.
انا فعلا في تلك اللحظة انتقلت
And in the corner of one of these -- one of my notes,
وفي احدي ملاحظاتي
is this note that says, when asked,
كانت افضل ملاحظه هي عندما سألت
what do you think of conventional foie gras?
ماذا تعتقد بان كبد الأوز التقليدي هو؟
What do you think of foie gras that
مارايك في كبد الاوز هذا
99.99999 percent of the world eats?
99.9999999 بالمئة من ما ياكل العالم
He said, "I think it's an insult to history."
كما قال ان هذا اساءة للتاريخ
And I wrote, insult to history.
وكتبت اساءة للتاريخ
I'm on the plane and I'm just tearing my hair out.
انا في الطائرة واحك راسي
It's like, why didn't I follow up on that?
لماذا لانتبع نحن ذلك
What the hell does that mean?
ماذا يعني ذلك
Insult to history.
اهانة للتاريخ
So I did some research when I got back,
فقمت ببعض الأبحاث علي ذلك
and here's what I found.
ووجدت ان
The history of foie gras.
تاريخ كبد الاوز
Jews invented foie gras.
ان اليهود من ابتكروه
True story.
قصة حقيقية
By accident.
بالصدفة
They were looking for an alternative to schmaltz.
وعندما كانوا يبحثون عن بديل لوصفة الاجداد الخاصة بهم
Gotten sick of the chicken fat.
لانهم اصبحوا مرضى بسبب دهن الدجاج
They were looking for an alternative.
وكانوا يبحثون عن حل
And they saw in the fall that there was this natural,
ووجدوا ان الحل في الطبيعة
beautiful, sweet, delicious fat from geese.
طعم جميل وسكري و لذيذ وجدوه في الاوز
And they slaughtered them, used the fat throughout the winter for cooking.
وقاموا بذبحها واستخدموا دهونها في فصل الشتاء
The Pharaoh got wind of this --
ثم استفاد فرعون من ذلك
This is true, right off the Internet.
هذه حقيقة من الانترنت
The Pharaoh got -- (Laughter)
حصل فرعون (ضحك)
I swear to God.
انا اقسم
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
The Pharaoh got wind of this and wanted to taste it.
حصل فرعون علي ذلك واراد تذوقه
He tasted it and fell in love with it.
تذوقها ووقع في حبها
He started demanding it.
وبدا في طلبها
And he didn't want it just in the fall, he wanted it all year round.
وارادها ليس فقط في الخريف ولكن علي طول العام
And he demanded that the Jews supply enough for everyone.
وطلب من اليهود ان يوفروا الكفاية لأي شخص
And the Jews, fearing for their life,
ولخوف اليهود علي حياتهم
had to come up with an ingenious idea,
قاموا بابداع فكرة ذكية
or at least try and satisfy the Pharaoh's wishes, of course.
او علي الأقل ليرضوا امنيات فرعون طبعا
And they invented, what? Gavage.
فابتدعوا التزقيم
They invented gavage in a great moment of fear for their lives,
في لحظة خوف علي حياتهم
and they provided the Pharaoh with gavage liver,
واعطوا فرعون كبد الأوز
and the good stuff they kept for themselves.
والأشياء الجيدة احتفظوا بها لانفسهم
Supposedly, anyway. I believe that one.
من المفترض ، على أي حال. وأعتقد أن واحدة.
That's the history of foie gras.
هذا هو تاريخ كبد الأوز
And if you think about it,
ولو فكرتم في ذلك
it's the history of industrial agriculture.
هذا هو تاريخ صناعة الزراعة
It's the history of what we eat today.
هذا تاريخ ماناكله اليوم
Most of what we eat today.
تاريخ معظم مانأكله
Mega-farms, feed lots, chemical amendments,
المزارع الضخمة ، والكثير من الأعلاف ، والتعديلات الكيميائية ،
long-distance travel, food processing.
السفر لمسافات طويلة ، وتجهيز الأغذية.
All of it, our food system.
كل هذا هو نظامنا الغذائي
That's also an insult to history.
ذلك ايضا اساءة للتاريخ
It's an insult to the basic laws of nature
هذا اهانة لابسط قواعد الطبيعة
and of biology.
وعلم الاحياء
Whether we're talking about beef cattle
سواء كنا نتحدث عن البقر
or we're talking about chickens,
او نتحدث عن الدجاج
or we're talking about broccoli or Brussels sprouts,
أو أننا نتحدث عن البروكلي أو براعم بروكسل ،
or in the case of this morning's New York Times, catfish --
أو في حالة نيويورك تايمز هذا الصباح الجديد ، سمك السلور --
which wholesale are going out of business.
في جملتها الخروج بالأعمال
Whatever it is, it's a mindset that is reminiscent of General Motors.
اي كان . انها العقلية التي تذكر جنرال موتورز.
It's rooted in extraction.
انها متجذره في علم الاستخراج
Take more, sell more, waste more.
خذ اكثر... بع اكثر... واتلف اكثر
And for the future it won't serve us.
ومستقبليا فهي لن تخدمنا
Jonas Salk has a great quote.
جونز سالك لديه مقولة رائعة
He said, "If all the insects disappeared,
لو اختفت كل الحشرات
life on Earth as we know it would disappear within 50 years.
الحية علي وجه الارض فسنختفي نحن بعد خمسين سنة
If human beings disappeared, life on Earth as we know it would flourish."
لكن لو اختفي الانسان فان الحياة علي وجه الارض ستزدهر
And he's right.
ولقد كان علي حق
We need now to adopt a new conception of agriculture.
نحن نحتاج لتبني مفهوم جديد للزراعة
Really new.
حقا جديد
One in which we stop treating the planet
مفهوم نتوقف فيه عن معاملة هذا الكوكب
as if it were some kind of business in liquidation.
كما لو انه نوع من التجارة المراد تصفيتها
And stop degrading resources under the guise of
ووقف اهدار الموارد تحت ستار
cheap food.
الطعام الرخيص
We can start by looking to farmers like Eduardo.
يمكننا البدء بالنظر للمزارعين امثال ادواردو
Farmers that rely on nature
مزارعين في الطبيعة حقا
for solutions, for answers,
لحلول واجوبة
rather than imposing solutions on nature.
احسن من طلب الحلول علي حساب الطبيعة
Listening as Janine Benyus,
والاستماع كما تسمع جين بينوس
one of my favorite writers and thinkers about this topic says,
واحدة من افضل الكتاب والمفكرين حول هذا الموضوع
"Listening to nature's operating instructions."
"الاستماع لتعليمات عمل الطبيعة"
That's what Eduardo does, and does so brilliantly.
ذلك ماكان يفعله ادواردو وفعله بذكاء شديد
And what he showed me and what he can show all of us, I think,
وذلك ما أرانا اياه ومايمكن ان نريه للجميع كما أعتقد
is that the great thing for chefs, the great blessing for chefs,
وذلك شي عظيم للطهاة ومباركة كبرى للطهاة
and for people that care about food and cooking,
ولكل من له اهتمام بالأكل والطهي
is that the most ecological choice for food
هو أن الخيار الأكثر الإيكولوجية للأغذية
is also the most ethical choice for food.
والخيار الأكثر اخلاقية
Whether we're talking about Brussels sprouts or foie gras.
سواء كنا نتحدث عن الأوز او دجاج بروكسل
And it's also almost always, and I haven't found an example otherwise,
وكما هي دائما الحال واي مثال في اي مكان
but almost always, the most delicious choice.
وكما هو دائما الخيار الافضل والألذ
That's serendipitous.
تلك هي الصدفة
Thank you.
شكرا جزيلا
(Applause)
تصفيق